<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: talks | Geshan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/categories/talks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://geshan.com.np/"/>
  <updated>2019-11-03T04:32:31+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://geshan.com.np/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geshan Manandhar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laracon AU 2019 overall a good experience]]></title>
    <link href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2019/11/laracon-au-2019-overall-a-good-experience/"/>
    <updated>2019-11-01T09:01:15+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://geshan.com.np/blog/2019/11/laracon-au-2019-overall-a-good-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my second Laracon, the first one was <a href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2016/08/number-laraconeu-2016-was-a-great-experience-overall/">Laracon EU 2016</a> which was one of the best conferences I have ever attended and spoken at. This blog post is a rundown of the talks of the first day of Laracon AU 2019 with slides from my talk, carry on reading…</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" data-echo="/images/laracon-au-2019/01-laracon-au-2019.jpg" title="Laracon AU 2019 stage" alt="Laracon AU 2019 stage"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Day 1</h2>

<p>This is the second <a href="https://laracon.com.au/">Laracon</a> in Australia, the first one was in 2018. There were just over 200 people who attended the first day. The speaker line up looked pretty interesting with more than a couple of first-time conference speakers. TBH, no one seemed like they were taking the conference stage for the first time</p>

<h2>Talks were great</h2>

<p>The day was started by <a href="https://freek.dev/">Freek</a>, it was great meeting him after Laracon EU 2016. His talk was titled “A way to structure a large Laravel app” which is very good. The pointers on using typescript and creating a domain (kinda sub-apps) inside your Laravel were the highlights for me.</p>

<p>Then <a href="https://twitter.com/michael_timbs">Michael Tims</a> took on the stage to show how to test fronted Javascript Apps. The highlight for me was “Contract testing” in this talk as I was familiar with the regular forms of testing like unit, integration and even mutation testing. After him, <a href="https://blog.maxsnow.me/">Max Snow</a> showed us his Laravel API boilerplate and how it makes creating APIs on Laravel easy. Then it was me on stage and details about my talk “Are logs a software engineer’s best friend? Yes &ndash; follow these best practices” are below.</p>

<p>After lunch, <a href="https://jessarcher.com/">Jess Archer</a> spread her knowledge of SPAs, the highlight for me was using JWT token in cookies. As I have done it in the past it was easier for me to relate to the concept. Then <a href="https://samgreenwood.me/">Sam</a> took the stage to show us the need for strict types and tools in PHP to do it. I liked the multiple tools he mentioned like <a href="http://psalm.dev">Psalm</a>. After him, <a href="https://jessbudd.com">Jess Budd</a> showed us how to write semantic HTML to build apps accessible with screen readers. The main takeaway for me here was semantic HTML not only improves accessibility but also add more SEO juice to your website.</p>

<p>After the break, <a href="https://amyskapers.tech/">Amy</a> took on the stage to show us the magic of CSS grids. The main highlight for me was it helped me demystify the seemingly magical CSS grids. Last but not least was <a href="https://jasonmccreary.me/">JMac</a> (creater of Laravel <a href="https://laravelshift.com/">Shift</a>) giving us important pointers to “Creating maintainable Laravel applications”. He had 10 points to do so. My main takeaway was “grok the framework” if I was writing Laravel every day that is something I would remember and follow :)</p>

<p>You can follow all the tweets/images at <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23laraconau">#laraconau</a> on twitter. Special thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/shanesmithau">Shane Smith</a> for his amazing threads on twitter. I don’t know how he is tweeting, listening and taking pictures at the same time :).</p>

<h2>My talk</h2>

<p>I think my talk went pretty well too. There was no time or provision to ask a question which is Ok. Some people came in later to ask their queries about logging and how to get started. I consider that the talk was warmly received by the audience with some laughs and a lot of attention.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" data-echo="/images/laracon-au-2019/02-laracon-au-2019.jpg" title="My talk about Logging at Laracon AU 2019" alt="My talk about Logging at Laracon AU 2019"></p>

<h2>Slides</h2>

<p>Below are the slides from my talk:</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="26f9b284425c4048a8aa587e155636ce" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>The slides are on <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/geshan/are-logs-a-software-engineers-best-friend-yes-follow-these-best-practices">slide share</a> too.</p>

<h2>Day 2</h2>

<p>Today is day 2 and let&rsquo;s see how it goes. <a href="https://twitter.com/marcusamoore">Marcus</a> is going to start the day.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Day 1 was good overall. One thing I noticed was the number of female attendees was quite low. This is something the organizers can work on else the venue, organization of the speakers and attendees was commendable. Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/michaeldyrynda">Michael</a> and the team for putting up such a great tech conference in Sydney bringing together like-minded technologists under the same roof. Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Logging best practices to get the most out of application level logging -- Slides]]></title>
    <link href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2019/03/follow-these-logging-best-practices-to-get-the-most-out-of-application-level-logging-slides/"/>
    <updated>2019-03-26T09:02:43+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://geshan.com.np/blog/2019/03/follow-these-logging-best-practices-to-get-the-most-out-of-application-level-logging-slides</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Logs from the application level are the only way your application talks back to you. Having proper logs with commendable search capabilities is like having a torch in a dark room.</p>

<p>Fully exploiting logs in case of any issues is very underrated. We as software engineers can utilize logs from the application to resolve issues as well as know the general health of the application.</p>

<blockquote><p>Logs can be instrumental to profile application performance too.</p></blockquote>

<p>I had written about <a href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/08/importance-of-logging-in-your-applications/">logging</a> some years back too. This post is focused on best practices you can follow when logging from the application level and how it can help you as a software engineer.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" title="what recruiters look for" alt="what recruiters look for" data-echo="/images/logging-best-practices/logging-bp.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Best practices at a glace</h2>

<p>Following are the main best practices for logging:</p>

<h3>1. Log information optimally</h3>

<p>Too much information is noise and too less information is inadequate. It is difficult to strike the balance of how much log is optimal but that is the challenge. In the case of microservices also think about traceability between services like using a unique request identifier. Another thing to keep in mind is logs are temporal, not permanent. As they are not stored in the database they usually have a life from some days to some weeks.</p>

<h3>2. Always follow severity levels</h3>

<p>An emergency means your on-call phone is going to ring at 2 AM in the morning but an info severity is something that won’t bother anyone. You have to agree as a team on some set standards like the <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5424">syslog one</a>.</p>

<h3>3. Structure your logs</h3>

<p>Have a structure in your log lines, like have a message and a context array to add more information about the message. Follow an agreed upon JSON standard for logging. This makes it easy to parse and search. You could even set more rules like the date is mandatory, a description cannot be more than 255 characters, extra information goes in the context. Having these simple rules makes it easier to find the log when in need. It is highly recommended to provide context with log lines like add the details of the order (things that are not sensitive of course) when logging that the order could not be shipped for instance.</p>

<h3>4. Write logs carefully  (don’t hamper performance)</h3>

<p>Make sure that adding logs does not add a lot of extra milliseconds to your response times. As far as possible write logs in an async way, logs could even be written locally in a log file and shipped using a log shipper to the service of your choice. You can also make use of tried and trusted library depending on the language/framework you are working with. Using queues could also be an option to ship logs but keep in mind the possible lag when viewing logs.</p>

<h3>5. Use the right tools for the job</h3>

<p>The tools and services you choose to ship, view, search and sort logs are your team’s choice. Depending on the budget, the appetite for using external services a team could use a fully self-managed stack like <a href="https://www.elastic.co/elk-stack">ELK</a>/<a href="https://www.graylog.org/">Graylog</a> or go full SAAS with services like <a href="https://logentries.com">Logentries</a>/<a href="https://sematext.com/logsene/">Sematext Logsense</a>. The main idea is to use the tools that fit your needs very efficiently. If you need almost real-time logs using a queue, for instance, might not be the best decision. So design your logging infrastructure and stack that fits your needs well.</p>

<h2>The slides</h2>

<p>I had done a talk at my workplace in February about “Logging best practices” and the slides from the talk are below:</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="4f33e89002cc4a29926808ef42457fc2" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>You can view the slides on <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/geshan/logging-best-practices">slideshare</a> and <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/geshan/logging-best-practices">speaker deck</a> too.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<blockquote><p>If a dog is a man’s best friend, logs are software engineer&rsquo;s best friend.</p></blockquote>

<p>Use logs to the fullest to get the most out of it and keep in mind the best practices about logging.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving from A and B to 150 microservices, the journey, and learnings [Slides]]]></title>
    <link href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/10/moving-from-a-and-b-to-~150-microservices/"/>
    <updated>2018-10-26T21:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/10/moving-from-a-and-b-to-~150-microservices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I gave a talk at #devopsdaysNewy on 24-Oct-2018. It was a great conference with lots of amazing people.
I want to thank the organizers for putting together such an amazing event. I want to extend the thanks to the sponsors who made it possible :). It was very good couple of days to meet new people and form a network. I think my talk on microservices went pretty good too. It was my second devops days and I enjoyed it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" title="Moving from A and B to 150 microservices, the journey, and learnings" alt="Moving from A and B to 150 microservices, the journey, and learnings" data-echo="/images/a-b-to-150-ms/150-ms-geshan.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The abstract</h2>

<p>Are you frustrated working with large, legacy and potentially lethal code bases? We were frustrated too,but in 4-5 years of time, we replaced A (front-end) and B (back-office) system with ~150 microservices. From the days of no tests and clumsy deployment process, we moved to each service with unit tests, CI and deploying with a bot. With the business buying in the process, we enabled the business to reach new heights. This talk reveals that journey and the things we learned along the way.</p>

<h2>The slides</h2>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="05a92573b3fc4221b6a17478ae0db2b2" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>Slides on <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/geshan/moving-from-a-and-b-to-150-microservices-the-journey-and-learnings">slide share</a></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I gave the same talk at Node Sydney <a href="https://www.meetup.com/node-sydney/events/cvdqzpyxmbjb/">September meetup</a> that went pretty well too. Hope to be able to give more talks in future and meet more interesting people.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adopt a painless continuous delivery culture, add more business value [Slides]]]></title>
    <link href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2017/08/adopt-a-painless-continuous-delivery-culture/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-02T03:17:30+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://geshan.com.np/blog/2017/08/adopt-a-painless-continuous-delivery-culture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Your work responsibilities boil down to 2 things, either add value to customers or save cost for the business.
Value to the business is always more important than the latest technical fad. If a feature is done (production
ready) but not deployed to production it is an opportunity loss for the business.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" data-echo="/images/continuous-delivery/geshan-devops--days-pdx-2017.jpg" title="Adopt a painless continuous delivery culture, add more business value [Slides]" alt="Adopt a painless continuous delivery culture, add more business value [Slides]"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Below are the slides of my
talk titled &ldquo;Adopt a painless continuous delivery culture, add more business value&rdquo; given today at
<a href="https://www.devopsdays.org/events/2017-portland/program/">DevOpsDays Portland 2017</a>:</p>

<h2>The Slides</h2>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="44a57cc9c1eb4c5a9ba087cea49dac78" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>Slides on <a href="http://bit.ly/cdbv-gm">slideshare</a></p>

<h2>The Video</h2>

<p>The video of the talk is below:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2oYPAHJwr6U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>The Abstract</h2>

<p>A continuous delivery of new features definitely adds value to the business, it should be effortless to the tech team too. 5 years back our sys-admin team was in Istanbul and the dev team was in Dubai. Even then changes were shipped periodically but the process was cumbersome. A stable delivery pipeline with tests, continuous integration and small atomic deployments with github flow gives us a leading-edge. The culture of logging and monitoring ingrained in our team helps us move fast. Now, we ask a chatbot to deploy our microservices several times a day to production. In this session, I will unveil details on how you can get started with a smooth continuous delivery pipeline one step at a time.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The first day of DevOps Days PDX 2017 was pretty impressive. Looking forward to day 2!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things I wished I knew as a junior developer for Developers Nepal Meetup #4 [Slides and Video]]]></title>
    <link href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2017/02/things-i-wished-i-knew-as-a-junior-developer-slides/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-08T03:31:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://geshan.com.np/blog/2017/02/things-i-wished-i-knew-as-a-junior-developer-slides</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being a senior software developer is more about the mindset and pro-activeness. Technical skills can take you to a point then you will be stagnant. To grow you need to learn in tech field. Above was the context for my talk titled &ldquo;Things I wished I knew as a junior developer&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" data-echo="/images/things-jr-dev/geshan-dn-meetup-4.jpg" title="Me speaking about Things I wished I knew as a junior developer at DN Meetup 4" alt="Me speaking about Things I wished I knew as a junior developer at DN Meetup 4"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Main points</h2>

<p>It mainly highlights the 10 points below:</p>

<ol>
<li>Solutions and value to business is much more important than the latest language/framework.</li>
<li>Be strong in the basics.</li>
<li>First, solve the problem. Then, write the code. - John Johnson</li>
<li>Writing simple and clear code is more difficult than writing magic code.</li>
<li>Code reviews help both the reviewer and reviewee.</li>
<li>(Automated) Testing is easier than debugging.</li>
<li>Automation is King.</li>
<li>Application logs + monitoring save your sleep.</li>
<li>Non tech things are very important like proactive communication, being on time etc.</li>
<li>You might not need that abstraction - like an ORM.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Slides</h2>

<p>I gave this talk on 4-Feb-2017 for Developers Nepal Meetup #4, the slides are below:</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="faca53aa9c854cd682eb08b64ddb168a" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>You can also view the slides on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/geshan/things-i-wished-i-knew-as-a-junior-developer">slideshare</a>.</p>

<h2>Video</h2>

<p>The video of the talk is below:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cLokEa545SY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>Meetup Report</h2>

<p>There were lots of participants making it a really good opportunity to network.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" data-echo="/images/things-jr-dev/dn-meetup-4-participants.jpg" title="Participants at DN Meetup 4" alt="Participants at DN Meetup 4"></p>

<p>It was great meetup to attend, speak and moderate the panel discussion.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://geshan.com.np/images/generic/loading.gif" data-echo="/images/things-jr-dev/dn-meetup-4-panelists.jpg" title="Open discussion panelists at DN Meetup 4" alt="Open discussion panelists at DN Meetup 4"></p>

<p>If you are interested more about the meetup you can view the meetup report <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1utAY2UyxNOzBKFbp8cfY4cbz6Np517_fVGO4VCVXdds/">here</a>.</p>

<p>More photos of the meetup can be viewed <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/sh/jeq76wzcaffg1ft/AABcnAJpd3Kk6HiEbt3XjgQ7a?dl=0">here</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>I hope you learned something new.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
